Guide to the Norton Nicholls Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Norton Nicholls papers
1750-1811
OSB MSS c 467
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2
(8 volumes)
The papers document aspects of the life and career of Norton Nicholls, especially his Grand Tour (1770-1773), his friendships, and his family relationships. Major correspondents include Jane Floyer Nicholls, Karl von Bonstetten, Thomas Gray, John Minifie, and Thomas David Boswell.
Nicholls, Norton, 1741?-1809
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Norton Nicholls Papers were purchased in 1983 on the Osborn Gift Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
NORTON NICHOLLS (1742-1809)
Norton Nicholls was born in Lisbon on February 24, 1742, the only surviving child of Jane Floyer Nicholls and Norton Nicholls. The family returned to London by 1745, but the elder Nicholls became bankrupt and abandoned his family, leaving only a small annuity for his wife. With the assistance of Charles Floyer, an East India merchant, Nicholls was educated at Enfield School, Eton, and Trinity Hall, Cambridge, receiving his LL.B in 1766. The death of Charles Floyer in that year severely reduced his income, and in the following year Nicholls was presented to the livings of Lound and Bradwell in Suffolk, which he retained until his death.
While at Cambridge, Nicholls was befriended by Thomas Gray, who advised him in his studies and encouraged him to pursue a career in the church. In 1770 he and Gray traveled through the Midlands together, and Nicholls kept a journal of that excursion. Gray encouraged him to make the Grand Tour, and in June 1771 Nicholls set out for what was intended to be a year in France, Switzerland, and Italy.
Nicholls remained abroad for two years, returning home in financial difficulties that were not resolved for many years. While traveling, he made several lifelong friendships, particularly with Count Charles Firmian, the Austrian minister at Milan; Charles de Bonstetten; James Ogilvy, earl of Findlater; and John Minifie.
He returned to Suffolk in the late spring of 1773 and settled with his mother at Blundeston, as there was no rectory in either of his parishes. He farmed his land, laid out ornamental gardens, pursued his interests in music and literature, and entertained often. While he never revisited the Continent, he made an extended visit to Scotland in 1779-80, possibly in the hopes of some employment with Lord Findlater. In 1786 he traveled to Ireland in the company of Lord Fitzwilliam, but again returned to Suffolk. Nicholls visited London for about two months in every year, attending operas, plays, and literary gatherings.
Jane Floyer Nicholls died in 1800. Nicholls's last years were spent quietly at Blundeston, where he attended to family matters, received a few friends, and corresponded with many more. Norton Nicholls died "from the sudden bursting of a blood-vessel" on November 22, 1809.
Scope and Contents
The Norton Nicholls Papers consist of 848 letters and a small number of miscellaneous papers documenting the life of the Reverend Norton Nicholls. The papers span the dates 1750-1811, with the bulk of the material dating from between 1770 and 1790.
The correspondence is arranged chronologically in eight bound volumes. The letters are numbered both in a single chronological sequence and separately within each volume. Only the former are used in the register. The miscellaneous personal papers are found at the end of volume 8.
The correspondence of Norton Nicholls provides a detailed picture of the daily life of a rural minister with literary interests during the last half of the eighteenth century. Somewhat over half of the letters in the collection are from Norton Nicholls to his mother Jane Floyer Nicholls; the remainder are nearly all to Norton Nicholls from a variety of friends and relatives. A few are copies of letters by Nicholls to others. (It should be noted that the Gray letters presently in the collection are copies of originals now at Eton.)
Nicholls's letters to his mother provide excellent documentation of his daily activities, financial affairs, and cultural interests. Early letters contain news about both the Nicholls and the Floyer families; much information about the Nichollses' income; descriptions of Nicholls's life and studies at Eton and Cambridge; and comments concerning his friendship with Thomas Gray. Several letters discuss Nicholls's interests in music and literature. For example, a 1760 note informs his mother that "The Nouvelle Heloise is scarcely worth your reading--and positively improper for my cousin Fanny."
There are approximately forty letters from Nicholls to his mother written during his Grand Tour, and these provide detailed descriptions of places and scenery, travel arrangements, and Nicholls's persistent financial problems. Those written from Italy contain much information about the daily lives of his friends and traveling companions, and on the social and political activities of the Milanese court, including a misunderstanding Nicholls had with a "Madame Balbi" while he was there.
The last letters from this period detail Nicholls's reluctance to return to Suffolk; in a December 1772 letter he exclaimed, "I am absolutely incapable of living forever at Blundeston! It appears dismal to me at this distance!" He did return early in the following year, however, and the remainder of his letters to his mother concern his daily life as rector of two parishes in Suffolk. Topics include financial matters, family members, parish business, farming, ornamental gardening, Nicholls's health, and social life in Suffolk. Letters written during his extended stay in Scotland comment on Scottish social life and customs, his cousin Fanny Floyer Erskine, and the Earl of Findlater. Nicholls's many visits to London are documented in letters describing operas, plays, amateur musicales, and dinners.
Letters from relatives in both the Floyer and Nicholls families are largely concerned with family news and finances. Most of the information concerning the elder Nicholls comes from these letters, including the report that "he died at Manilha sometime after the capture of that place" (25 Sep 1767). As the Nichollses were financially assisted by their relatives, many of the letters they received contained financial advice. A letter of 1771, for example, from George Nicholls discusses Norton's proposed journey to Italy and questions "How far it may be proper in Norton's state in life."
Nicholls's correspondence from his friends is concerned with other subjects. The letters of Thomas Gray discuss literature, Nicholls's studies, and Gray's health, and offer advice to Nicholls concerning his clerical career. Through Gray, Nicholls became a friend of Charles de Bonstetten, whose letters contain news of Gray, descriptions of Bonstetten's own travels, and political gossip. Also during his years at school, Nicholls met John Wheler, who like him was ordained in the late 1760s, and began a friendship which continued until Wheler's death. Wheler's letters discuss family news, London social events, sermons, politics, and literature.
Nicholls first became acquainted with many of his lifelong correspondents while on his Grand Tour, including Count Charles Firmian; James Ogilvy, later earl of Findlater; Count Wilseck; and Captain John Minifie, "an Englishman in the Empress's service." There are almost four dozen letters by Minifie in the collection, detailing his travels and his political observations on subjects ranging from the American Revolution to the attempted reforms of Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor. Other Continental correspondents include Leopoldina Stahremberg, the duchess di Castelpagano, and Ipolito Salviati Caprara. Their letters usually contain news of acquaintances, social gossip, and descriptions of cultural events.
Other correspondents include Thomas David Boswell, with whom he was an executor of William Johnson Temple's estate; Octavius Temple; Dawson Turner; and John Casamajor. A group of letters written in 1799 and 1800 document a serious quarrel among Nicholls and several people concerning a insulting comment Nicholls had supposedly made about the mistress of the duke of Queensbury. The letters of Robert Reeve, Thomas Thurtell, and other farmers comment on such matters as the 1802 Enclosure Act riots in Suffolk, "the Hydra of the French Revolution," and the increasing difficulty Nicholls and other ministers had in collecting tithes. Nicholls's continuing interest in music and literature is apparent in the correspondence of Miss S. A. Glover, Mrs. Anderson, and Mary Gurdon.
The last volume of the correspondence also contains a variety of personal papers. These include Nicholls's will, its probate, and a final account of the estate; stray notes on his Italian tour; several elaborate epitaphs on relatives; and law notes in the hand of John Wheler. There are also lists of songs, pictures, and sculptures "exhibited at Richmond this season" and about fifteen copies of miscellaneous poems, including "Verses to Clarinda on Fortune-Telling, by Lord Hervey," "Advice from an Aunt to a Niece," and "On Marriage with an Old Woman."
Church lands -- England; Clergy -- England -- Finance, Personal; Country life; English literature -- 18th century; Families -- England -- Domestic relations; Friendship; Gardening -- England; Grand tours (Education); Landlord and tenant -- England; Mothers and sons; Music -- Great Britain -- 18th century; Blundeston (Suff.); France -- Description and travel -- Early works to 1800; France -- Description and travel; Great Britain -- Description and travel -- Early works to 1800; Great Britain -- Description and travel; Great Britain -- Religion -- 18th century; India -- History -- British occupation, 1765-1947; Italy -- Description and travel -- Early works to 1800; Milan (Italy) -- History -- 1535-1859; Suffolk (England) -- Description and travel; Suffolk (England) -- Intellectual life; Clergy; Austen, Edward; Bonstetten, Charles Victor de, 1745-1832; Boston, George, Baron. (Irby); Casamajor, John; Castelpagano, Duchess of.; Firmian, Karl Josef, Graf von, 1716-1782; Gray, Thomas, 1716-1771; Gurdon, Mary; Joseph, Holy Roman Emperor, II, 1741-1790; Minifie, John; Nicholls, Jane Floyer; Nicholls, Norton, 1741?-1809; Findlater, James Ogilvy, Earl of, approximately 1689-1764; Queensbury, William Douglas, Duke of, 1724-1811; Turner, Dawson, 1775-1858; Wheler, John; Wilseck, Count; Baker-Holroyd, John, Earl of Sheffield; Erskine family; Nichols family; Church of England ( Benefices); Church of England -- Clergy -- Salaries, pensions, etc.; East India Company; Eton College; Temple, William Johnston, 1739-1796
- Correspondence, 1750 Jun 27
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School, 1750 Jun 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School, 1751 Jul 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School, 1752 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School, 1752 Jun 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School; family, 1752 Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School; Augustus Floyer, 1753 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School, 1753 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School, 1753 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School; Augustus Floyer, 1755 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School; family, 1755 Apr 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Norton Nicholls to [Reverend] Allen. Enfield. Concerns Enfield School, [1755] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College; Edward Barnard, 1756 Oct 24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Charles Floyer to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Fort George, India. Concerns Indian affairs; Norton Nicholls, 1757 Jun 25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College, 1757 Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College, 1757 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College, 1758 Jun 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College; Edward Barnard, 1758 Jun 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College; Sir Lucas Pepys, 1758 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College, [1758] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Norton Nicholls to Augustus Floyer. Eton. Concerns Eton College, [1758] (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College; Edward Barnard, 1759 Jan 19 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College; Edward Barnard, 1759 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College, 1759 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Charles Floyer to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Conjiveram. Concerns Indian affairs, 1759 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College; Edward Barnard, 1759 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Eton. Concerns Eton College, 1759 Nov 27 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Cambridge University, 1760 Jul 9 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Cambridge University; literature, [1760] (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Norton Nicholls to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns family; mysterious letter to father, 1761 Aug 10 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Cambridge University, 1762 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Harwich. Concerns Holland travels, 1763 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Utrecht. Concerns Holland travels, [1763 Mar] 19 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Utrecht. Concerns Holland travels, [1763] Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. York. Concerns advowson, 1763 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns gardening; sermons, [1763] (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns advowson; family business; literature, [1763 Dec] (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns literature, [1763-64?] (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns William Mason, [1764] Jan 19 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Jacob Kirkman to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns music., [1764] Jan 23 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Ditchley Park. Concerns Cambridge University, 1764 Jun 13 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Richmond. Concerns family, 1764 Jul 6 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Murrill Green. Concerns Richard Owen Cambridge, [1764] (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Malmhead. Concerns William Johnson Temple, [1764] Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Cambridge University, 1764 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Southampton. Concerns London, 1764 Nov 19 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Concerns London; Samuel Johnson, 1765 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Thomas Gray, 1765 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Richmond. Concerns family, 1765 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns family, [1766 Apr] (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Richmond. Concerns Richard Owen Cambridge, 1766 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Thomas Gray to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns William Johnson Temple, 1766 Aug 26 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Ashbourne., [1766 Sep 12] (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns family health, 1766 Sep 23 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Nottingham, n.d.. (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns family business, 1766 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Michael Turner to Norton Nicholls. Putney. Concerns family business, 1766 Oct 25 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - James Preston to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns family business, 1766 Oct 28 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns family, 1767 Jan 19 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Cambridge University., 1767 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Swaffham. Concerns William Johnson Temple, [1767] Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Dorchester. Concerns family, [1767] Sep 5 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Charles Floyer to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Calcutta. Concerns family; Indian affairs, 1767 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Salisbury. Concerns clergy; Suffolk, 1767 Oct 7 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Ipswich. Concerns Suffolk, 1767 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - George Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Ditchley Park. Concerns advowson; family, 1767 Nov 2 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Yarmouth. Concerns advowson, 1767 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns advowson; Suffolk, 1767 Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Ditchley Park. Concerns advowson, 1767 Nov 25 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns William Johnson Temple, 1767 Dec 31 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Cambridge University, 1768 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns William Johnson Temple; William Mason, 1768 Feb 3 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns music, [1768] May 29 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns Thomas Gray; William Barrett, 1768 Aug 3 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns Cambridge University, 1768 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Cambridge University, 1768 Nov 8 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns William Johnson Temple, 1768 Dec 18 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. London. (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Thomas Gray, 1769 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge., 1769 Jan 26 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Cambridge, 1769 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Thomas Gray, 1769 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Thomas Gray, 1769 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge., 1769 Jun 7 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Norton Nicholls to Thomas Gray. Blundeston. Concerns Thomas Gray; Augustus Henry Fitzray, Duke of Grafton, [1769] Jul 3 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Charles de Bonstetten to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns London; music, 1769 Nov 2 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - John Wheler to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns family, 1770 Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Charles de Bonstetten to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Thomas Gray; John Wheler, 1770 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - John Wheler to Norton Nicholls. London., 1770 Feb 16 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Charles de Bonstetten to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns Cambridge University, 1770 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge University. Concerns Charles de Bonstetten, 1770 Mar 20 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - John Wheler to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns Charles de Bonstetten; France, 1770 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Norton Nicholls to Thomas Gray. London. Concerns Charles de Bonstetten, [1770 May 25?] (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - John Wheler to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns France; family; mentions letters of recommendation for Grand Tour, 1770 Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Charles de Bonstetten, 1770 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Charles de Bonstetten; gardening, 1770 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns Charles de Bonstetten, 1770 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns gardening, 1770 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Charles de Bonstetten to Norton Nicholls. Paris. Concerns Thomas Gray; Cambridge University, 1770 Jun 24 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - John Wheler to Norton Nicholls. Horncastle. Concerns Thomas Gray, 1770 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Thomas Gray; Charles de Bonstetten; gardening, 1770 Sep 14 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - John Wheler to Norton Nicholls. Bath., 1770 Oct 28 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Charles de Bonstetten to Norton Nicholls. Bern., 1770 Nov 15 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. n.p. Concerns Charles de Bonstetten, 1776 Nov 25 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Suffolk; France, 1771 Jan 26 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. n.p. Concerns France, 1771 Feb 24 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Charles de Bonstetten to Norton Nicholls. Bern. Concerns Bern; Switzerland, 1771 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. Cambridge. Concerns Charles de Bonstetten; William Johnson Temple, 1771 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns William Johnson Temple, 1771 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Charles de Bonstetten to Norton Nicholls. Bern. Concerns Thomas Gray, 1771 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - John Wheler to Norton Nicholls. Lowestoft. Concerns Suffolk, 1771 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - George Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Ditchleys. Concerns Norton Nicholls, 1771 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Nathaniel au Rix to Norton Nicholls. n.p. Concerns Norton Nicholls; Nicholls leaves on Grand Tour, [1771] Jun? (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. n.p. Concerns Thomas Gray; Suffolk, 1771 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Paris., 1771 Jun 27 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Thomas Gray to Norton Nicholls. London. Concerns Thomas Gray, 1771 Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - J. F. Erskine to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Alloa House. Concerns family, 1771 Jun 30 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Frances Erskine to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Alloa. Concerns family; Augustus Floyer, 1771 Jul 28 (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - John Spurgeon to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Yarmouth. Concerns Thomas Gray; Eloquent letter on Gray's death, 1771 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Charles de Bonstetten to Norton Nicholls. Bern. Concerns Norton Nicholls, 1771 Sep (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Norton Nicholls to Jane Floyer Nicholls. Bern. Concerns Thomas Gray; Horace Walpole, 1771 Sep 5 (Box 1, Folder 120)